Hello, my name is rob trace and I'll be here talking tuesday about
the new http to protocol and how it's implemented in windows ten?
So, we're going to talk about first just...real brief summary of...http
to is important why we spent the time and effort implement windows ten?
Then we will talk learn overview of hp to how it works how it's divx information
...one and then lastly what it means to be
in windows tended how it actually shows up for a developers and for a customers?
why did we are go to all this effort to define a new internet standard few years ago there
was a huge realization that performance matters a lot of studies were done by
sites like google by microsoft by amazon about the effects of slow
site performance about slow out performance on user behavior and what we found
was that money is defined a lot by site performance
slow sites users click away they go you somebody else's site?
Through that investigation there was also realization that hp one-one was holding back
side performance the way that hp one-one transfers data across
the internet causes inherent slowness is affected very heavily
by latency and it was a problem for basically taking
site performance to where it is where we wanted to get...
It's also very large problem for mobile networks
and as they started to emerge we saw more and more high latency networks more and
more users using these latency networks and more and more sites slowness.
In addition to that over the last three years so there's been a very large movement towards using
tls by default microsoft themselves announce that they're going to be moving all of their
sites overs dls you'll see moves by similar companies who
...throughout the industry and
we you migrate to dls also is impacted by the latency problem and
expand the makes the problem with hp one-one connections even greater.
Lastly the web is evolving and there's a
need for more bidirectional communications there's a need for
cheaper quicker faster protocols to for us to enable new site
developing new application development this is really what was
behind the motivation for starting on a protocol hp too.
So, when you look at the drafter hp to you'll see
...section on why what was the motivating factors what
...the requirements that...trying to achieve with
...new protocol and the number one thing was to make a user perceive
...difference
...performance and what we want to ulysses users have the feeling that...apps
...their sites are actually performing faster the second thing is that it's impossible
to develop a new protocol if it doesn't work over the existing infrastructure
so primary goal of hp to is to be able to traverse existing internet and all
the things that are out there whether it's proxies whether it's isp?
Gateways all of these different technologies
are deployed today any new protocol has to work over the
...this infrastructure and
then the last thing was a real definable goal to work with
today's content we wanted to be able to have a protocol that worked
with the applications with the sites with the content as it was developed today
does not mean that content...involved in the future to be better with http
to but it does mean that we wanted to take an existing site runner with
a new transport and then be able to see the user benefits out of
it right away gave us something that we could use immediately that within
evolve application...development for the long-term.
So, what is http to essentially primarily hp
to is a different mapping of the http transport in
the http semantics to tcp and word enables
...multiplexing...heart this gives us the ability to send and receive data
of multiple request receive multiple responses over the same...
channel in addition to that we've included header compression in the protocol which is going to mean
...less biter sent over the wire very important for some scenarios like
...of mobile broadband or we have
...links or slow links and the last one is server push
...server push enables a site a server-side to anticipate
request and...send the content and pri prime the client for the requests are going-to be
coming throughout the application these three features are really the heart of what
http to is going to be?
a negotiated protocol and this is one of the reasons that is compatible with the web
...deployed today?
It works over the standard hp ports port ad import for forty-three
at works with the schemes are existing today in http
in https it is exactly the same as a spone one-in-one
...before it so when my application requests.
Aac resource over https.
By the fall we will use port for forty-three.
If I use http will stay on port eighty.
In addition to this it also will support ...are either has a custom port like eighty,
eighty so it works the same way as a should be
one-one and therefore a work with the same content and retain the same semantics...
second thing is just really important want to highlighted http to the specification works
with both http scheme and https scheme.
Meaning that it is possible to set http to across the internet in clear text.
How this works and how this is negotiated is...I use
...http uri will negotiatetcp connection first?
And, then we'll negotiate tls
it's exactly the same processes you get when you use http one-one.
when the client since the tls client hello we included a lp
n extension that will have a protocol identifier h
to nh to essentially is the client
advertisement that is possible talked me over http to?
The server takes the client...looks at that it supports http to
aswell will return the client the server hello with
the eyal piano...to at this point both sides of excepted that they support
each...and we'll start with
...ha settings frame in http to the minute
...tls complete with this negotiation this means that
a site running and older web server that only supports http one-one
we'll see this tls negotiation will not reply
with each to the client will continue normally on http one-one brain
...is an upgraded server will then see the
...to marker will then respond with its own
extension protocol string and those connection will procedure http
...very simple for clear text
...similar of the we start with
http negotiation we set up the connection and then we send our
first request over http one-one and...request is allowed to
included upgrade header that indicates the client is available
over http to when the server sees that...header the
server then can send back a response saying that great wilson bakke switching
protocol responses and then the every subsequent request on that?
On that connection will be over hp
...essentially the client on...next packet will send out to settings frame.
So, what this enables is that both hp to pcs
at http transports can be negotiated and can be supported
essentially an environment where the client can support hp one-one hp to
...can connect to any server regardless of what they support?
Now for windows ten we're not going to be supporting the http
...text initially this is something that we anticipate will evolve and
we will implement over the long-term...not going to be in the first release of windows...
So, connections this is really at again at the heart of the
...after we've decided between the client-server that we're going to use http
to we're going to...connections and there's a new concept in hp
to called a stream now stream is essentially a request response
pair but we manage multiple stream to them
...connection to hp one-one how this worked was client sets
up a connection and goes ahead makes the first request that request has
to fully complete before they can make their second connection
they're second request so on for the third and the fourth.
Network clients...one-one to overcome this...blocking is that will
...multiple connections so when I have one connection is that has
a request in-flight and I have a second requests that I need to make a little bit
of second connection and the third and the fourth.
What this does is we'll see a lot of tcp connections coming...the client and
they're all subject to...slow start they're all subject to latency of setting up
to connection in particular with tls will have latency of setting up the
...us portion...connection?
...too it's very different we set up one connection so
we pay the cost of setting up the connection only wants.
And, then once we've set up that connection we can initiate multiple
streams and these streams can be delivered out of order and,
they can be requested...to a hundred at a
time protocol actual allow for more but the hundred as the default so will happen now with the
client as we q up requests we can put those on the wire and send them off the server right
away and then the server can respond back in the order that the server
things that makes the most sense.
Meaning that if I have content is ready to be sent right away and I have an
...tcp connection I can start sending that data the client right now well I
maybe off calculating a different response so what happens is now we
can fully optimize the transport between the client and the server depending on what's
most important or the things that are queued up for that the...requests.
The other piece of the protocol that comes in here is a decline can advertise a priority which
means that the client can tell the server what is the most important
thing to deliver back to it so now the server has context about what the client
wants and can again make these decisions on how to send best...back to the client?
the streams very simple there are...streams are initiated by the client and then
there are push trains which will coverages...initiated by the server.
The client streams are always an odd number strain the...terms are always an even number
So, the stream lifecycle is also important concept and it really starts
with...a client wants to go ahead and request resource so the client opens
their connection and they want to create a stream so what
that does that puts the stream into the open state...decides it's going to
...resource it opens a stream essentially and then goes ahead and sends out
...header frame this create an open stream from both standpoint the client and the server.
And, that stream then continues as long as the client is continuing to
say transmit data when the client is done transmitting it's headers field or if it is
...has data associated with the request is done transmitting data
...and...stream message and it as
an stream flag so once the client sends...stream flag that
stream is closed from the clients perspective...that it is sent all the data it's going to
...and the server should know that and...it does that make that makes the
session half close local the server has the same process as a server sends back headers
and data when it is done...can send...stream flac so again that
and stream floodwaters...by the client becomes have closed remote?
And,...and then
...stream transmits transitions into a close state when both sides have
...stream and closers the other way...stream can transition directly from open
to closed is that a client or server consent a reset stream.
Message and we send research string that means that stream must be torn down and,
all-state and all processing on it needs to...
Stream can transition directly from open to closed.
The other state that will have is the idle state and the
idle state is one we're using server push meaning...the
server is intending to push resources to the client and how that works is
a server initially sends a message...push promise and that push promise indicates
all of the resources that the server wants to push to the client each one of those resources
creates a stream on...client?
That is an idle state the
client is waiting for more data from the server at that point.
Now what happens is that the push promise opens a stream
entitle as the server sends data or the client
consent things like a reset stream on-message that the stream
will move from and I'll stay to an open state.
...those streams are then reserved when the server has sent those
push...the messages as data transmits
it goes from open and then we go into the and stream flags where we end up in the
have close states or we end up in a closed aone both sides of done transmitting on
a particular stream and then we clean-up after that so what this is
there's a simple life-cycle to every stream...really extends to the extent of
...sent a request and then the response and once
data is all done both sides can indicate that were done and...the stream we can
clean-up the stream without closing the connection and we
definitely want to keep the connection open until all of the streams all of the
...responses of come in a little bit different model them with hp one-one.
The next feature is inhp to
...compression and...compression is essentially taking
a header and we're going to start replacing it with literal values and what we do is we
generate to tables there's a built-in static table of
certain limited number of headers that are
pre indexed in the system and those headers might include method
...get...might include the...http?
And, what they...there indexed into a
table that is essentially at the start of every connection there's a second table
is a dynamic table and that is as the lifetime of a connection progresses we
can add entries into the compression table that are going to be reused,
for example, a cookie or maybe the user agent
string and how this progresses is that the client?
As they send headers can then indicate whether this is
...reference to item that already exist in the table or
whether it's a literal value that may potentially be indexed into the table.
The static table never changes but the dynamic table is a running
list of how what the current state of the connection is the list is ordered
means that the first entry goes in is the first entry goes
out is also limited in size so the size of the table is defined
...connection setup that goes on between the...the server?
What will happen is that as we add new items to table
if the table exceeds the maximum size
we will then take out the entries that came
in first so it's basically a rolling list and it is order is also
possible to have multiple entries of the exact same header in
the dynamic table meaning that I could put user agent or some other?
Header into the table multiple times and multiple times can be with the same value or with different
values meaning I could put multiple cookies into the...at the same time.
So, the operation itself there are basically two types of headers now there's
index header which means that...reference to header by supplying
...index name and what happens is on the encoder side
one more sending data we can look for the header in the table and we can
replace the full header with...and then we transmit that to the other side
of the connection the decoder will find that index and
more replace it with what the value is in the table?
This is what the heart of the compression this is how we reduce the number of bytes rashes
...on the wire the other way is we send a literal which is a full header and then
...that literal can be marked in three ways number one is
add this to the table so we added to
the dynamic table so if we have a new header that we want to add to the table we can just
...this to the table.
If we want to have a...item that we should not add to the table
...market is do not add to the table and then the third state is never add this to
the table and that's really an instruction for all of the intermediaries between the client
and the server to not add this to their table all the way through and leave it
as a literal throughout the connection and.
What this
does is by having this mechanism where we indicate from the sender?
What...what not...to the table we can have a
matching table between the client the center for both the send and receive paths?
So, as a client I will end up with a...table where I
add values depending on what I want to have into the table
and marking them as a literal that say add to the table...server as
a receiver will then respect those markings on the literal messages
and create a and identical table on the server-side that process works
in reverses well so when the server is the sender and
transmitting response there's a separate table
those maintained for this flow and the server then controls what gets
...that table and the client receives those literals and respects and built-in identical table.
This scheme came out of the fact
...previous iterations of protocols they were using a
smaller standard compression scheme ig zip but this is found to be vulnerable
...a crime attack and the value of the hvac is that it's
an efficient protocol it'sa way to get
...of compression but without...vulnerabilities that were in the
...solutions previously.
So, the third major feature here with...hp to server push
...server push does it allows the server to anticipate what the...to ask
for and send them to the client to...warm the cash.
And, this is really useful in this case where I have a lot of static resources
...are part of building a page where I can start sending those back to the
client before the client even asks for them so while I have space in my connection I can
send back resources that I already know the client is going to ask for based on whatever
...his first request was how this works is the
client always starts every connection with the settings frame and they make
...get in side of stream.
Every server push has to
be anchored to a open stream you can't start pushing unless a
...is actually made a request so once the client makes a request.
The server application can then determine the
...this...going to make a bunch of other requests and I want to go ahead
and cinema resources now to make sure that he's going to
get them as fast as possible so the server application can call api
...within windows from is
and from esp dot net that says please push these resources what this doesn't
...windows system is...creates an artificial get and we push that get back up to the application
...sees it just like ...client ask for
an from there that will create within the stack a push promise
...push promises a list of all of the resources that we intend to push
for advertising to the client here's a list of things that we want to push
...this is the list of the server application generated and called
...into esp dot net so we send this message across
the list of all the resources we intend to push and then.
We can begin pushing on the strains each one of
those push promises create a stream in
idol state and then we start to push on them we create
we actually moved into an open state this was from a stream lifecycle a couple of slides ago.
pushing these things then the server can also respond to the initial get in
the same time the main thing is that the server cannot close.
The stream cannot send
...stream until it is done with all the pushes that are anchored to that per
...so it will have to that first get...
first stream has to remain open while the other pushes complete on the client-side with
the server push what happens is the client collects all of the pushes in an in memory
cache they don't push directly into the http cash and then as
we hit the resources we need to acquire in the other code that
ascent say that there are links in htm the index study html
or spx those things are requested their pulled out in memory cache without
...the wire...served back to the client application very quickly and then we go to a normal
cash processing where we can added to the hp cash and we can
...the resources normal
...just as if we were in normal operation we just eliminate the network latency time.
how is...should be to...web applications there are a few ways that we
anticipate the first thing is that when we start to open hanging gets they don't block
connections so we have one connection now we can use it for as many
...resources we'd like to we have this huge number of streams we can open up
we can now send out a get that we don't expect to be fulfilled
for some time and it doesn't block to tcp connection now we can do other things on
that same connection without having to have something just opened in waiting for the
...request to be filled the second thing is that today to increase parallelism a lot of
sites on have shorted their content they've created multiple domains so the
client will create many open connections and we can have lots of
requests and parallel this is no longer necessary with hp
too so where resources are held on the same server
they can now be put into the same domain and then we will get better connection re-use
we won't be flooding the...say with tcp and tls connections?
We have server push and there's going to be lots of different uses for server push the
most basic examples obviously a website that knows wants to push resources based on the first
There will be other uses and we anticipate that
people will come up with lots of creative ways to help their clients make their applications more
efficient faster by using server approach.
There is an opportunity now to use
smaller smaller bits of content no longer does a request and response
...tcp connection where latency will cause us to not send
as much data we can...we can take content and break it up into smaller
chunks that may be more cache mobile than having one large say
inline chunk and by doing...what you're going to do is you're going to enable some
clients to cash resources even proxies or
intermediaries to cash resources more efficiently than they do necessarily
today and therefore will end up with over the long-term less dataset so
this is an opportunity for us to better use the web as it was define.
then lastly you're going to have fewer connections but...be longer...this means a lot less connection
setup time this means a lot less state for maintaining a number of
connections means a better...the network as a whole underneath
us it's a better model for using the actual tcpip protocol.
So, in windows ten how does hp to show up with the original goal that hp
too was useful with existing content with existing applications
and over the existing web...possible implement hp to in a
very transparent way to the application ecosystem so we have implemented
hp to in the when I net client stack and the http.
Server stack and in this way that hp to is
handle completely by windows the operating system itself.
And, then over the top of that we have all on number of application platforms.
And, all of these get http to support automatically spartan,
for example, have hp to support on by default automatically so
when we hit a server that supports a should be to this will get
note negotiated and them the connection will
continuous hp to when botha server and the client support the same thing for
...ww a web view web oc?
The one exception and one of the exceptions in here is the web
of see platform and here because of some of our legacy applications
we have hp to off by default it can be enabled by
registry key so that we can take advantage of it...
if it's appropriate for the application.
Which also in some of the development platforms the windows web dot http?
And,...hr platform...spaces again is on by
...existing application written to these platforms will offer http to
the server automatically
and if the server happens to support fantastic
then will negotiated and we'll use the...in a dot net?
We're working now to try and include http to support for the
windows ten store applications and we're hoping that we'll be able to bring this
in the short-term with windows ten.
We want to...in basically the same way where the application doesn't have to do anything special
they just get it automatically and they can take advantage of the protocol and,
also in for a applications...specifically use
hp too and some of the advantages of it those things will be available as well.
There on the server-side
...to support being built...automatically I ask
...automatically and esp dot net applications
...an automatically the exception to that is with
...dot net if we want to do server push from the from the application
on the server-side they will actually have to identify the resources and
...new code to indicate to the stack what they want to push
is a change is not a huge change to
...application but it is a new model of deliver the content.
...places where we're not going to have hp to support by default the first one
is in when http so is not going to be available in when http in windows
ted is something that will be working on for future releases and then the other
place is inlegacy web platform application so things that
use some of our legacy platforms are not going to get hp to support automatically
and, this is just basically a sense of focus for us we
want to work on the highly hit the main use platforms and things like the ie
in the spartan or the windows dot web dot http.
Also there's another session here on
do networking development platforms and they're going to cover specifically how-to
enabling use http when needed so I highly recommend that talk as well?
So, where do we go from herethe biggest thing grab...tryout
http to your existing applications like we talked about your existing sites they
should be able to take advantage of hp to you can go ahead and grab the server
you can install your site on top of windows ten server and hp to support will be
on by default and available to any klein who asks
for it you can test it and make sure that the promise of hp to the better performance
works with your content take your applications common
...for the windows ten store in which case you will get
hp to support automatically again try them out see how they works the other work with...
services that are advertising http to support...a lot that are and development now?
Give us feedback where we're open were looking forward to having as use...platform?
Thank you very much.